Thomas Szasz Papers
Thomas Szasz Papers
- Writings by Szasz
  - Articles
    - Mind as Noun, Mind as Verb: Psychiatry's Futile Quest for the "Written Troubles of the Brain", undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 168)
    - Mind, Brain, and the Problem of Responsibility, 2000; reprint Society May 2000 (Box 168)
    - Mind Tapping: Psychiatric Subversion of Constitutional Rights, Oct 1962; reprint from American Journal of Psychiatry (Box 168)
    - Mind: What Matters, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 168)
    - The Mirage of Anticapitalist Freedom, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 168)
    - Mises and Psychiatry, Apr 2002; published article from Medical Opinion and Review (Box 168)
    - Mises's Mistakes About Madness, undated; published article from Medical Opinion and Review (Box 168)
    - Models of Madness, 1 Dec 1977; published article from The Listener (Box 169)
    - Moral Conflict and Psychiatry, Summer 1960; reprint and published article from Yale Review (Box 169)
    - The Moral Dilemma of Psychiatry: Autonomy or Heteronomy?, 1964; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from December issue of American Journal of Psychiatry (Box 169)
    - The Moral Physician, 1975; published article from The Center Magazine March/April 1975 (Box 169)
    - A Moral View on Suicide, 1989; research material, publisher correspondence, typescript with revisions, published article from Suicide: Understanding and Responding (Box 169)
    - The Morality of Drug Controls, 1984; typescript drafts with revisions, proof copy; 3 folders (Box 169)
    - Mr. Carter's Misconceptions about the Iranian "Crisis", 1980; undated; typescript with revisions (Box 169)
    - My Views on Psychiatry, 1993; typescript, published article from Eastern European Medical Journal, published also as "Nézeteim a Pszichiátriáról" (Hungarian) (Box 169)
    - The Myth of Drug Abuse Treatment, 1991; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 170)
    - The Myth of Mental Illness, 1960; 1966; research notes, typescript drafts, published article from American Psychologist February 1960, Medical Opinion and Review April 1960 and from Médecine et Hygiène (in French) July 30, 1962 (Box 170)
    - The Myth of Mental Illness Fifty Years Later, May 2011; reprint from RC Psych (Box 170)
    - The Myth of Mental Illness: A Further Examination, 1974; publisher correspondence, typescript (Box 193)
    - The Myth of Mental Illness: Three Addenda, Summer 1974; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from the Journal of Humanistic Psychology (Box 170)
    - The Myth of Psychotherapy, 1972; 1974,; 1978; typescript drafts with revisions, published article from Fortschritte der Klinischen Psychologie 2 (in German) 1972, American Journal of Psychotherapy October 1974, Libertarian Review March 1978, Movement Summer 1978; 2 folders (Box 170)
    - The Myth of the Rights of Mental Patients, Jul 1989; research notes typescript drafts with revisions, published article from Liberty; 4 folders (Box 170)
    - The Myth of Treatment, Fall 1991; reprint from The Drug Policy Letter (Box 171)
    - The Nature of Pain, 1955; reprint from A.M.A. Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry (Box 171)
    - The Negro and the Mentally Ill, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 171)
    - The Negro in Psychiatry: An Historical Note on Psychiatric Rhetoric, 1970-1971; typescript, reprint from July issue of Journal of Psychotherapy (Box 171)
    - New addictions for old, 29 May 1978; reprint from Inquiry (Box 171)
    - The "New" Field of Forensic Psychiatry, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 171)
    - New Ideas, Not Old Institutions, For the Homeless, 1985; typescript drafts with revisions, published article from June 7 issue of Wall Street Journal (Box 171)
    - A New Screwtape Letter, 1980; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 171)
    - NNN, undated; typescript (Box 171)
    - Nobody Should Decide Who Goes to the Mental Hospital, Summer 1978; published article from Co-Evolution Quarterly (Box 171)
    - Non-Coercive Psychiatry: An Oxymoron. Reflections on Law, Liberty, and Psychiatry, 1989; 1991; typescript drafts with revisions, published article from Journal of Humanistic Psychology Spring 1991 (Box 171)
    - Non-Medical Psychotherapy, 1961; publisher correspondence, typescript (Box 171)
    - Normality, Neurosis and Psychosis, October/December 1957; reprint from Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease October (Box 171)
    - A Note on Psychiatric Rhetoric, Jun 1965; reprint from American Journal of Psychiatry (Box 171)
    - A Note on the History of Electric Shock Treatment, undated; typescript (Box 171)
    - A Note of the Mechanism of Trauma Re-enactment Dreams, undated; typescript (Box 171)
    - Obstructing Therapeutic Justice, 1978; typescript with revisions (Box 171)
    - Oedipus: From Rex to Complex, 1977; research notes, typescript drafts with revisions (Box 171)
    - Oedipus: Myth or Madness?, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 171)
    - Oil and Opium: Divine Justice?, 1974; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 171)
    - On Autogenic Diseases, May 2004; reprint from The Freeman (Box 171)
    - On Involuntary Psychiatry, 1975; typescript, published article from the August 4 issue of The New York Times (Box 171)
    - On Mr. Buckley, Mr. Gilmore, and Suicide, undated; typescript (Box 171)
    - On Not Giving A Fish to a Starving Man, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 171)
    - On Preventing Psychopathology: A Libertarian Analysis, 1982; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 172)
    - On Retarded Thinking About the Retarded, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 172)
    - On the Attribution of Mental Incapacity, 1990; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 172)
    - On the Evil of Jonestown, 1978; typescript with revisions (Box 172)
    - On the Experiences of the Analyst in the Psychoanalytic Situation, Apr 1956; reprint from Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association (Box 172)
    - On the Future of Psychotherapy, January/February 2000; published article from New Therapist (Box 172)
    - On the Legitimacy of Psychiatric Power, 1982; typescript drafts with revisions, published article from the October issue of Metamedicine (Box 172)
    - On the Prevalence of Mental Illness: A Dissenting Opinion, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 172)
    - On the Psychoanalytic Theory of Instincts, Jan 1952; reprint from Psychoanalytic Quarterly (Box 172)
    - On the Psychology of Pain, 1968; typescript drafts with revisions; 2 folders (Box 172)
    - On the Theory of Psycho-Analytic Treatment, 1957; typescript, reprint from The International Journal of Psycho-Analysis (Box 172)
    - On Translating Karl Kraus: A Reply to Professor Harry Zohn, 1977; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 172)
    - The Only Right the Mental Patient Needs: The Right to Reject Psychiatry, 1983; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 172)
    - Open Doors or Civil Rights for Mental Patients, Nov 1962; reprint from Individual Psychology (Box 172)
    - An Open Letter to Blue Cross/Blue Shield, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 172)
    - Opium and Orientals, 1973; typescript with revisions (Box 172)
    - Oral Mechanisms in Constipation and Diarrhea, 1951; reprint from The International Journal of Psycho-analysis (Box 173)
    - The Origin of Psychiatry, 1994; typescript, published article from History of Psychiatry (Box 173)
    - The Origins of the 'Scientific' Study of Sex, 1982; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 173)
    - Our Despotic Laws Destroy the Right to Self-Control, Dec 1974; published article from Psychology Today (Box 173)
    - Out of the Dark Ages, undated; typescript (Box 173)
    - Pain and Pleasure, 1988; typescript drafts with revisions, peer review; 2 folders (Box 173)
    - Pain and the State, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 173)
    - The Painful Person, Jan 1968; reprint from the Journal-Lancet (Box 173)
    - Panaceas and Panapathogens: From Pharmacology to Pharmacarchy, 1973; typescript with revisions (Box 173)
    - Paradise Tossed, Apr 1988; published article from Omni (Box 173)
    - The Paradox of Behaviorism, 1994; typescript (Box 173)
    - Paresis and Plunder: The Models of Madness and Anti-Psychiatry, 1975; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from The University of Essex Noel Buxton Lecture (Box 173)
    - Parity for Mental Illness, Disparity for the Mental Patient, 1998; typescript (Box 173)
    - Patient Beware, 1971; typescript with revisions, published article from the April issue of JAMA (Box 173)
    - The Patient Has No Rights, 1978; typescript with revisions (Box 173)
    - Patient or Prisoner?, Jan 2002; reprint from Ideas of Liberty (Box 174)
    - The Patient Self-Determination Act, The Mental Health Act and the Mental Patient, 1998; galley proof of article for The Lancet (Box 174)
    - The Patient, The Doctor, and the State: Authenticating the Sick Role, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 174)
    - Patricia Hearst: The Twice-"Brainwashed" Heiress, 1976; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 174)
    - Patriotic Poisoners, 1976; research notes, typescript drafts with revisions, published article from the November/December issue of The Humanist (Box 174)
    - Paying Last Disrespects to Tennessee Williams, 1983; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 174)
    - The Perils of Prohibition, 1995; typescript, galley proofs (Box 174)
    - A Person's Life Belongs to Himself, 5 Jan 1975; published article from The Washington Star-News (Box 174)
    - Persuading Persons: Rhetoric as Remedy, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 174)
    - Peter Bourne's Quaalude caper, 30 Oct 1978; published article from Inquiry (Box 174)
    - The Philosophy and Theology of Medicine, 1977; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 174)
    - Physician Assisted Suicide: A Deceptive Euphemism, 1998; typescript, reprint from Washington Times (Box 174)
    - Physiologic and Psychodynamic Mechanisms in constipation and Diarrhea, March/April 1951; reprinted from Psychosomatic Medicine (Box 174)
    - The Plague on Both Their Houses, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 174)
    - A Plea for the Cessation of the Longest War of the Twentieth Century - The War on Drugs, 1988; typescript, published article from the Autumn issue of The Humanistic Psychologist (Box 174)
    - Point/Counterpoint: Should Alcohol and/or Drug Abusers Be Legally Coerced into Treatment?, 1983; typescript, published article from June issue of The U.S. Journal (Box 174)
    - A Point of Protest, Jun 1989; published article from The Salisbury Review (Box 174)
    - A Policeman in the Schools, Oct 1967; reprint from This Magazine Is About Schools (Box 175)
    - The Political Legitimation of Quackery, Mar 1998; published article from Reason (Box 175)
    - Political Pharmacology: Thinking About Drugs, Summer 1992; reprint from Daedalus (Box 175)
    - The Political Use of Psychiatry in the United States: the case of Dan White, 1981-1982; typescript with revisions, published article American Journal of Forensic Psychiatry (Box 175)
    - Politics and Mental Health: Some Remarks Apropos of the Case of Mr. Ezra Pound, Dec 1958; published article from American Journal of Psychiatry (Box 175)
    - Politics in Perspective, 1974; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 175)
    - The Politics of Addiction, August/September 1989; reprint from Focus (Box 175)
    - The Politics of Pain: Pain, Hunger, and Freedom, 1978; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 175)
    - The Politics of Pedocracy, 1996; typescript (Box 175)
    - The Politics of Poisoning, 1978; typescript with revisions (Box 175)
    - Portrait of a Secular Moralist, 27 Nov 1965; reprint from The New Republic (Box 175)
    - A Position Statement on Commitment, undated; typescript for The American Psychiatric Association and National Association on Mental Health (Box 175)
    - Power and Psychiatry, 1981; typescript with revisions, reprint from May/June issue of Society (Box 175)
    - Prescription for Control, 1 May 1978; reprint from Inquiry (Box 175)
    - The President as Psychiatrist, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 175)
    - The President's Commission on Mental Health, 1978; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 175)
    - Prettifying the Plantation: Contract, Command, Craziness, 1981-1982; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 175)
    - Prevention Through Political Action and Social Change, 1981; reprint from The Vermont Conference on Primary Prevention of Psychopathology (Box 175)
    - A Priest for President?, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 175)
    - The Private Madhouse, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 175)
    - The Problem of Privacy in Training Analysis, Aug 1962; reprint from Psychiatry: Journal for the Study of Interpersonal Processes (Box 175)
    - The Problem of Psychiatric Nosology, Nov 1957; reprint from The American Journal of Psychiatry (Box 175)
    - The Problems Facing Psychiatry, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 175)
    - Progress in Pain Relief, Sep 2000; reprint from Ideas on Liberty (Box 176)
    - Proposed Position Paper on the Protection of the Individual from Involuntary Psychiatric Intervention, 1969; typescript with revisions for ACLU Central New York Chapter (Box 176)
    - The Protocols of the Learned Experts on Heroin, 1981; research notes, typescript drafts with revisions, published article from July issue of The Libertarian Review (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Aspects of Vagotomy I, Feb 1948; reprint from Annals of Internal Medicine (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Aspects of Vagotomy II, July/August 1949; reprint from Psychosomatic Medicine (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Aspects of Vagotomy III, May 1952; reprint from Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Aspects of Vagotomy IV, Dec 1949; reprint from Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry (Box 176)
    - The Psychiatric Assault on Religious Freedom, 1984; research notes, publisher correspondence, typescript with revisions (Box 176)
    - The Psychiatric Classification of Behavior: A Strategy of Personal Constraint, 1966; typescript, reprint from The Classification of Behavioral Disorders (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Degradation Ceremonies, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Diagnosis, Psychiatric Power, and Psychiatric Abuse, 1994; research notes, publisher correspondence, reprint from Journal of Medical Ethics (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Diversion in the Criminal Justice System, undated; proof (Box 193)
    - Psychiatric Diversion in the Criminal Justice System, undated; typescript (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Drugs: Help, Harm or Burden of Choice?, 1991; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 176)
    - Psychiatric Expert Testimony Its Covert Meaning and Social Function, Aug 1957; reprint from Psychiatry: Journal for the Study of Interpersonal Processes (Box 177)
    - Psychiatric Interventions As Social Degradation Ceremonies, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 177)
    - Psychiatric Justice, 1989; typescript, published article from British Journal of Psychiatry and reprints (Box 177)
    - Psychiatric Peonage, 27 Jul 1960; typescript for New York Times (Box 177)
    - The Psychiatric Presidency, 1978; typescript drafts with revisions, published article from November 18 issue of Inquiry (Box 177)
    - Psychiatric Self-Defense, 1983; typescript, published article from May issue of Reason (Box 177)
    - Psychiatric Slavery, 1985; publisher correspondence, typescript drafts with revisions (Box 177)
    - "Psychiatric Terror in Canada", undated; typescript with revisions (Box 177)
    - The Psychiatric View of Mental Illness: An Illustrative Example, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 177)
    - The Psychiatric Will: A New Mechanism for Protecting Persons Against "Psychosis" and Psychiatry, 1982; typescript drafts with revisions, galley proofs, reprint from July issue of American Psychologist; 3 folders (Box 177)
    - The Psychiatric Will: Whose Will Is It Anyway?, 1983; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 177)
    - La Psychiatrie est Devenue un Religion, undated; reprint from Notre Société undated (Box 178)
    - Psychiatrie: Rhetorik und Wirklichkeit, 1986; reprint from SOG 1986 (Box 178)
    - The Psychiatrist: A Policeman in the Schools, Oct 1971; reprint from This Magazine is About Schools (Box 178)
    - The Psychiatrist as Accessory to Murder, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 178)
    - The Psychiatrist as Accomplice, Apr 1978; Apr 1985; published articles from Inquiry and Freedom (Box 178)
    - The Psychiatrist as Double Agent, Oct 1967; published article from Trans-Action (Box 178)
    - The Psychiatrist as Moral Agent, 1980-1981; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from Whittier Law Review; 2 folders (Box 178)
    - A Psychiatrist Views Mental Health Legislation, 1970; reprint from Washburn Law Journal (Box 178)
    - Psychiatrists vs. Gays, Aug 2 and 20, 1979; published article from Inquiry (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry: A Clear and Present Danger, 1974; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from Spring issue of Mental Hygiene (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry and dissent, 4 Mar 1978; published article from Spectator (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry and Freedom of Religion, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry and Politics: A Reply to Hutschnecker, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry and Responsibility, 1985; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 178)
    - Psychiatry and Social Control, January/February 1991; published article from The Humanist (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry and the Control of Dangerousness: On the Abracadabra Function of the Term "Mental Illness", 2003; typescript (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry and the Death Penalty, undated; research notes, typescript and handwritten (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry and the Denial of Evil: Defining Misbehavior as a Brain Disease, 1993; research notes, typescript with revisions, reprint from April issue of Pacific Law Journal (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry and the Unequal Protection of the Laws, undated; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry as Ideology, 1965; reprint from The Rationalist Annual (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry, Ethics, and the Criminal Law, Feb 1958; reprint from Columbia Law Review (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry -- in Black and White, 1969; typescript with revisions (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry in Public Schools, 1963-1964; reprint from The Humanist 1963, from National Review March 12, 1963 and from Teachers College Record October 1964 (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry in the Age of AIDS, 1989-1990; published article from Reason, December 1989, and from The Psychiatric Times, November 1990 (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry in the 1970s, 1980; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry, Psychotherapy, and Psychology, Nov 1959; published article from AMA Archives of General Psychiatry (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry: Rhetoric and Reality, 1985; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from September 28 issue of The Lancet; 2 folders (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry, the Law, and Social Control, 1969; published article from Summer issue of University Review (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry, the State and the University, undated; typescript drafts; 2 folders (Box 179)
    - Psychiatry, the State and the University, undated; typescript drafts; 2 folders (Box 180)
    - Psychiatry's Threat to Civil Liberties, 1963; research notes, typescript drafts with revisions, published article from March 12 issue of National Review (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis and Suggestion: An Historical and Logical Analysis, 1963; typescript, reprint from August issue of Comprehensive Psychiatry (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis and Taxation: A Contribution to the Rhetoric of the Disease Concept in Psychiatry, 1964; typescript, reprint from October issue of American Journal of Psychotherapy (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis and the Autonomic Nervous System, Apr 1952; reprint from The Psychoanalytic Review (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis and the Rule of Law, 1968; reprint from Summer issue of The Psychoanalytic Review (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis as Method and as Theory, 1958; reprint from Psychoanalytic Quarterly (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis as Religion: Psychoanalytic Theory as Ideology, Psychoanalytic Practice as Cure of Souls, 1986; research notes, typescript drafts with revisions; 4 folders (Box 180)
    - Psychoanalysis: Modified Purified and Basic, Apr 1961; reprint from Contemporary Psychology (Box 181)
    - Psycho-analytic Training, 1958; reprint from International Journal of Psycho-analysis (Box 181)
    - Psychoanalytic Treatment as Education, Jul 1963; reprint from A.M.A. Archives of General Psychiatry (Box 181)
    - Psychodrama in the White House, 1979; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from December issue of The Libertarian Review; 2 folders (Box 181)
    - The Psychology of Bodily Feelings in Schizophrenia, January/February 1957; reprint from Psychosomatic Medicine (Box 181)
    - The Psychology of Persistent Pain, 1968; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from Pain (Box 181)
    - Psychomanagerial Despotism, undated; typescript (Box 181)
    - Psychopathology, Liberty, and Society, undated; typescript (Box 181)
    - Psychosomatic Aspects of Salivary Activity, 1950; reprint from Life Stress and Bodily Disease (Box 181)
    - Psychotherapy: A Socio-Cultural Perspective, Aug 1966; reprint from Comprehensive Psychiatry (Box 181)
    - Psychotherapy: Its Past, Present and Future, 1966; typescript (Box 181)
    - Purifying America, 12 Apr 1982; published article from Inquiry (Box 181)
    - A Questionnaire Study of Psychoanalytic Practices and Opinions, Sep 1963; reprint from Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease (Box 181)
    - Quod Licet Jovi…, 1971; typescript with revisions (Box 181)
    - The Rapist as Patient, 1978; typescript drafts with revisions, reprint from June 26 issue of Inquiry (Box 181)
    - Re-Storing the Mentally Ill, undated; typescript (Box 181)
    - Reagan Should Let the Jurors Judge Hinckley, 6 May 1981; photocopy of published article from the Washington Post (Box 181)
    - Das Recht des Menschen auf sein Heroin [The Right to Heroin], 1 Jun 1980; photocopy of Penthouse (Germany) article (Box 181)
    - Reflections on Medical Ethics, 1975; typescript (Box 181)
    - Reflections On Psychopharmacology, 1982; typescript with revisions (Box 181)
    - Reflections on the Insanity Defense, 1982; typescript drafts with revisions (Box 181)
    - Reflections on the Panamanian Invasion, undated; typescript with revisions (Box 182)
    - "Rehabilitating" Galileo ?, 1984; typescript drafts with revisions, published article from March 12 issue of Time (Box 182)
    - The Religion Called "Psychiatry", 1987; research notes, publisher correspondence, typescript drafts with revisions, published article from Second Opinion; 2 folders (Box 182)
    - Remembering Masturbatory Insanity, May 2000; published article from Ideas on Liberty (Box 182)
    - Remember Patients' Civil Rights, 3 Apr 2003; published Op Ed from Seattle Post Intelligencer (Box 182)
    - Renting Time is Not Treatment, 1993; typescript for Washington Post (Box 182)
    - Reply to Professor Kendall, undated; research notes, typescript with revisions (Box 182)
    - Response to Clum, Sep 1987; reprint from American Psychologist (Box 182)
    - Rethinking Suicide, 1999; proof for July issue of Ideas on Liberty (Box 182)
    - Rethinking the Care of Mental Patients, 1997; typescript (Box 182)
    - Rewriting History: John Hinckley and Leon Czolgosz, 1981; research notes, typescript drafts with revisions (Box 182)
    - The Rhetoric of Rejection, 1961; typescript with revisions (Box 182)